## KRISTINA ULICNA

PhD Student (Year 2 / 4) @ UCL

London, United Kingdom

kristina.smith.ulicna@gmail.com

+44(0)7754385111 (UK)

in linkedin.com/in/KristinaUlicna

twitter.com/KristinaUlicna

github.com/KristinaUlicna

## Computer Skills

Strongest programming language: Python

- Machine learning libraries: skimage, sklearn, tensorflow 2.0, keras, CSBDeep
- Standard & scientific libraries: jupyter notebooks, numpy, scipy, pandas, json, matplotlib, pyplot, plotly, h5py, xml.tree

Work comfortably in *LaTeX* (with overleaf), & *Sigmaplot Statistics* (t-test, ANOVA)

#### Analysis of **DNA sequencing** data:

- SnapGene software: vector construction
- · CLC workbench: Sanger sequencing
- Nanopore sequencing platform interface

## Laboratory Skills

#### Molecular biology & vector construction:

- PCR (also colony, sequential, nested)
- Plasmid preparation (mini- & midi-prep)
- Restriction endonuclease gene cloning
- Gateway cloning & Gibson Assembly
- · Preparation & purification of mRNA
- Cell-free protein synthesis (PURExpress)

#### Cell engineering & tissue culture:

- Stable cell transfection via lipofection & lentiviral & retroviral transduction
- Colony selection with titrated antibiotics
- Tet(Dox)-inducible gene expression
- · Cell fractionation & organelle isolation
- Induction of cell differentiation (DMSO)
- Cell culture (passaging) with cell lines: HeLa, HL60, CH0, HEK-293, MCF-7 / 10A, MDA-MB-231, HMLER, LNCaP, HaCaT

#### Cell-based assays & imaging platforms:

- Cell proliferation assay (IncuCyte ZOOM live-cell analysis system)
- Colorimetric cell viability assay (MTT)
- Ratiometric [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] release assay (Fura-2)
- Fluorimetric Cat-S release assay (MCA)

## Gene expression detection methods:

- Primer-based reverse-transcription PCR
- · SDS-PAGE, Western (dot) blotting
- Immunocytochemistry (IF cell staining)
- Extra- & intracellular flow cytometry
- Fluorescence-activated cell sorting & FACS-sorted clonal cell line expansion

## Summary

As a **PhD researcher** at UCL, I apply my **programming & laboratory skills** in a multi-disciplinary project combining cancer cell biology, computational single-cell tracking & **deep learning**. I focus on **Python software development** for **large data analysis** to identify biological patterns influencing **cancer cell cycling** control mechanisms. I am a practical, detail-oriented scientist with **cell engineering** background & **leadership skills** demonstrated in individual & collective settings, which I gained through work experience in **biomedical research** groups in **academia** & **industry** in the UK & US, and through my involvement in **volunteering & community projects**.

#### Education

Oct 2018 – Sep 2022 (expected)

## PhD in Biosciences, BBSRC LIDo DTP Programme, UCL | London, UK

- Provisional Thesis Title: "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning: Tracking Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Lines", advised by G. Charras & A. Lowe
- Fully funded via London Interdisciplinary Doctoral Training Partnership (LIDo DTP)
- Yale School of Medicine Collaborative Student 2020 (exchange postponed to 2021)
- Merit-based Scholarships: Talents of the New Europe '19, Students to the World '19

Sep 2014 -Jul 2018

## BSc Biomedical Science (Hons), King's College London | London, UK

- First Class Hons (76%) Biomedical Science with Extramural Year in Pharmacology
- Awards & Scholarships: Desmond Tutu Scholarship '14, Best Lay Article Award '15

## **Teaching Experience**

Jun 2020

## "Introduction to Deep Learning" @ UCL Cancer Domain | London, UK

- Delivered a beginner-friendly <u>masterclass</u> for 100+ interdisciplinary scientists with real-life examples of deep learning-based bioimage analysis from my PhD project
- Demonstrated deep learning benefits, contrasted deep learning to computer vision methods, emphasised fundamentals of 'learning' component & current challenges

Mar 2020

## Graduate Teaching Assistant, BIOC0016 module @ UCL | London, UK

- Co-designed an iPython-based <u>practical session</u> for 70+ undergraduate students for introductory concepts in bioimage analysis, bioinformatics & machine learning
- Tutored students to hand-label mini-dataset & train simplified CNN to classify cell mitotic state based on chromatin condensation level from fluorescence readouts

## Research Experience

Mar 2019 -Present

## PhD Researcher, the "DeepTree" project @ UCL | London, UK

- Ulicna K., Vallardi G., Charras G. & Lowe A. R. (2020). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. bioRxiv 2020.09.10.276980
- Co-developed a robust, supervision-free, deep learning-based tracking pipeline for deep lineage analysis of large time-lapse microscopy data in non-/cancer cell lines
- Prepared publication manuscript outlining <u>computational framework</u> (U-Net, CNN, bTrack multi-object tracking algorithm) & its applicability for cell cycle research
- Analysed multigenerational lineage trees (>20,000 single cells) to identify heritable proliferation characteristics which predispose cell to acquire cancer-like properties
- Sep 2016 -Aug 2017

## Industrial Trainee @ Crescendo Biologics Ltd. | Cambridge, UK

- Engineered novel, universal tool cell line for early drug discovery, i.e. phage display selection & functional screening of antibody fragment oncology therapeutics
- Presented project outcomes to senior scientists & company management board

Jun 2016 -Sep 2016

## Research Intern, CRUK @ University of Cambridge | Cambridge, UK

• S. Bohndiek Lab: Characterised anti-angiogenic drug effects via breast cancer cell-based growth, viability assays to evaluate oxygen role in cancer progression

Jun 2015 -Aug 2015

## Visiting Scholar, Whitehead Institute @ MIT | Cambridge, USA

• R. Weinberg's Lab: Investigated determinants of cancer cell invasion, metastasis & tumour stroma immunomodulation upon epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition

#### Leadership & Teamwork Experience

Sep 2019 – Present

# Student Ambassador, LIDo PhD Programme @ UCL | London, UK - Outlined programme structure & shared own experience with new student cohorts

Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects

Jul 2019

#### Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects

Rotating Delegate @ The European Union Council | Helsinki, Finland • Shortlisted by Slovak Youth Council as representative at EU Youth Conference series

Aug 2017

#### Young Delegate, Youth Assembly @ United Nations | New York, USA

• Selected on basis of volunteering activity & community service project involvement

## Language Skills Slovak native proficiency Czech bilingual proficiency

IELTS & iBT TOEFL language test certificates

full professional proficiency

limited working proficiency

High-school certificate; German evening classes

#### Hobbies & Interests

- · Ballroom dancing; standard & Latin style (UK national partner competitions level)
- Bachata & salsa social dancing (int/adv)
- Long-distance running (half-marathons)
- Playing tennis (competitively at school)
- 'Stress-release' boxing & martial arts

#### General -

**English** 

- Member of the London Stem Cell Network (since Dec 2019)
- Member of the University of London DanceSport Society (since Sep 2019)
- Member of the British Pharmacological Society (since Sep 2017)
- Slovak (European Union) driving licence | B type (since Jun 2013)
- First aid training course certificate (Mar 2013)

## Academic Referees —

## **Prof Guillaume Charras**

- PhD project advisor; Professor in Cell & Tissue Biophysics @ London Centre for Nanotechnology & Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web: https://charraslab.com/
- g.charras@ucl.ac.uk Email:

#### Dr Alan R. Lowe

- PhD project advisor; Al for Science Fellow @ The Alan Turing Institute & Associate Professor of Biophysics at Inst. of Struct. & Molec. Biology @ UCL
- http://lowe.cs.ucl.ac.uk/ Weh:
- a.lowe@ucl.ac.uk Email:

#### **Prof Geraint Thomas**

- LIDo PhD Programme Deputy Director; Professor of Biochemistry at Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- https://www.lido-dtp.ac.uk/ Weh:
- Email: g.thomas@ucl.ac.uk

## Leadership & Teamwork Experience (cont'd)

Mar 2017	Category Finalist, Telegraph STEM Awards @ GSK   London, UK Presented an early-stage healthcare team invention pitch to expert industry judges
2015 - 2017	Jury Member, LEAF Award @ LEAF   Bratislava, Slovakia • Shortlisted self-driven, talented students with community involvement in jury team
2016 - 2018	University Mentor, Talent Guide @ LEAF   Bratislava, Slovakia • Counselled college choices with gifted high-schoolers & edited personal statements

2010	Counselled college choices with girted high-schoolers & e	uitea personai statements	
Specialist Trainings & Summer Schools			
Dec 2019 - Jan 2020	Jumping Rivers Ltd.  • Two intermediate courses: 'Machine Learning with Pytho	London, UK on', 'Python & Tensorflow'	
Aug - Sep 2019	University of Hong Kong Practical course 'Advanced Imaging: Deep Learning in Li	Hong Kong, China ve Imaging & Cell Biology	
Jun - Jul 2019	University of Genova  • 'Machine Learning Crash Course' covering theoretical for	Genova, Italy undations & core concepts	
Sep - Oct 2016	University of Cambridge  • Two beginners courses: 'Solving Biological Problems', 'St	<b>Cambridge, UK</b> tatistical Analysis' using R	
Jun – Jul 2012	Johns Hopkins University Interactive class <i>The History of Disease'</i> by Centre for T	Baltimore, USA alented Youth (CTY JHU)	

## Contributed & Invited Talks

Contributed Talks: with research project "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning - Tracking the Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Populations" as a PhD research student

Jan 2021	<ul><li>Imperial College London</li><li>Virtual Seminars in Biomedical Science</li></ul>	<b>London, UK</b>   virtual
Dec 2020	<b>London Stem Cell Network &amp; Francis Crick Institute</b> • London Stem Cell Network 3rd Annual Symposium (poster)	<b>London, UK</b>   virtual
Nov 2020	<ul><li>UCL, University of London</li><li>UCL Bioimage Analysis Interest Group</li></ul>	<b>London, UK</b>   virtual
Nov 2020	<ul><li>#PyLadies Dublin</li><li>Python Software Foundation Pro Network Meetup</li></ul>	<b>Dublin, Ireland</b>   virtual
Sep 2020	Society of Biomolecular Imaging & Informatics (SBI²)  • SBI² High Content 2020 7th Annual Conference	Boston, MA, USA   virtual
Jun 2020	<ul> <li>UCL &amp; Birkbeck, University of London</li> <li>Institute of Structural &amp; Molecular Biology Postgraduate Syn</li> </ul>	<b>London, UK</b> nposium   virtual
Nov 2019	Birkbeck, University of London • Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Friday Wrap Talk	London, UK
Oct 2019	King's College London  • Quantitative Systems Biology Workshop 2019	London, UK
Feb 2019	Francis Crick Institute	London, UK

• Francis Crick Institute & UCL Graduate Student Symposium (poster)

Invited Talks: with research project "Lipoproteins as a Vehicle for Targeted Drug Delivery in Photodynamic Therapy of Cancer" as a pre-college student with university collaboration		
Sep 2015	Universal Expo Milano 2015  • Presented ongoing research as national team member to expert & lay audience	
May 2014	Intel International Science & Engineering Fair   Los Angeles, USA • Shortlisted finalist at world's largest pre-college science competition (poster talk)	
Jul 2013	International Congress of Young Investigators   Zaragoza, Spain • Invited as 'Absolute Winner at the Festival of Science & Technology' & recipient of 'The Special Award by the Dean of the Faculty of Natural Sciences'	

Festival of Science & Technology

# **Selected Publications**

Nov 2012

Ulicna, K., Vallardi, G., Charras, G. & Lowe, A. R. (2020). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. bioRxiv 2020.09.10.276980 DOI: 10.1101/2020.09.10.276980 | GitHub: https://github.com/KristinaUlicna/DeepTree

Recognised as 'Best Scientific Project at Festival of Science & Technology 2012'

| Bratislava, Slovakia